<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science on Daniel Emaasit</title>
    <link>/categories/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science on Daniel Emaasit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Daniel Emaasit</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Principled AI with Probabilistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2018/05/22/principled-ai-with-probabilistic-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/05/22/principled-ai-with-probabilistic-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>(Note: Cross-posted with the Haystax Technology Blog.)
At Haystax Technology, we are proponents and early adopters of principled approaches to machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) for cybersecurity.
We use the term &amp;lsquo;principled AI&amp;rsquo; to describe what we call our model-based approach, which is built on coherent mathematical principles. These principles help us keep our AI transparent, explainable and interpretable. Most importantly, they enable our systems to quantify uncertainty, unlike the black-box approach of deep neural networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Processes with Spectral Mixture Kernels to Implicitly Capture Hidden Structure from Data</title>
      <link>/post/2018/03/19/gaussian-processes-with-spectral-mixture-kernels-to-implicitly-capture-hidden-structure-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/03/19/gaussian-processes-with-spectral-mixture-kernels-to-implicitly-capture-hidden-structure-from-data/</guid>
      <description>(Note: Cross-posted with the Haystax Technology Blog.)
Several scientific fields such as insider-threat detection, highway-safety planning, often lack sufficient amounts of time-series training data for the purpose of scientific discovery. Moreover, the available limited data are quite noisy. For instance Greitzer and Ferryman (2013) state that ”ground truth” data on actual insider behavior is typically either not available or is limited. In some cases, one might acquire real data, but for privacy reasons, there is no attribution of any individuals relating to abuses or offenses i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICYMI: My talk on Introduction to Probabilistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2017/08/14/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/08/14/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>Incase you missed it, here is a recording of my talk on Introduction to Probabilisitic Machine Learning at the Las Vegas R &amp;amp; Data Science Meetup groups.
I introduced probabilistic machine learning and probabilistic programming with Stan. I discussed the basics of machine learning from a probabilistic/Bayesian perspective and contrasted it with traditional/algorithmic machine learning. I also discussed how to build probabilistic models in computer code using a new exciting programming paradigm called Probabilistic Programming (PP).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In case you missed it: My Webinar on Model-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 07:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;Model-Based Machine Learning&amp;rdquo;, here is the recording.
  Apologies for the poor quality of the video. Domino Data Lab&amp;rsquo;s webinar platform suffered a service degradation while recording the event. The webinar slides may be found below.
 If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. Finally, I would like to thank Daniel Enthoven and Daniel Chalef from Domino Data Lab for setting up this webinar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gallery of ggplot2 Extensions</title>
      <link>/post/2016/07/29/a-gallery-of-ggplot2-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 02:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/07/29/a-gallery-of-ggplot2-extensions/</guid>
      <description>A couple of months ago, I announced the ggplot2-extensions website which tracks and lists extensions built on top of the popular R visualization package ggplot2.
Now, I wanted to make it even easier for R users to filter and search for these extensions and so I have added a Gallery page. You can now search packages based on a filter like: if it&amp;rsquo;s on CRAN; or if it&amp;rsquo;s for a particular task e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinar: Model-Based Machine Learning and Probabilistic Programming using RStan</title>
      <link>/post/2016/07/16/webinar-model-based-machine-learning-and-probabilistic-programming-using-rstan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 22:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/07/16/webinar-model-based-machine-learning-and-probabilistic-programming-using-rstan/</guid>
      <description>I am glad to announce that I shall be presenting a live webinar with Domino Data Labs on July 20, 2016 from 11:00 - 11:30 AM PST on Model-Based Machine Learning and Probabilistic Programming using RStan. If you are interested in adopting machine learning but are overwhelmed by the vast amount of learning algorithms, this webinar will show how to overcome that challenge. This blog post describes most of the material we will cover in the webinar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incase you missed it: My Talk at the United Nations Global Pulse Workshop</title>
      <link>/post/2016/07/07/incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 23:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/07/07/incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my talk at the 2016 Data Science Africa Workshop organized by the United Nations Global Pulse Lab, here is the recording. My talk was titled &amp;ldquo;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&amp;rdquo;.
 You can download slides for my talk from here.
 There were also talks from my colleagues at IBM Research - Africa including Oliver Bent, Simone Fobi and Skyler Speakman who gave a general overview of the work we are doing in our lab in Nairobi, Kenya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Preview of My Talk for the Data Science Africa Workshop organized by the United Nations</title>
      <link>/post/2016/06/28/a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:36:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/06/28/a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to be invited by the United Nations Global Pulse lab to speak at the 2nd Data Science Africa Workshop scheduled to take place in Kampala, Uganda from 30th June to 1st July. The theme of this workshop is &amp;ldquo;Using data science to monitor and achieve the global goals (UNDP goals) in Africa&amp;rdquo;. I will be speaking particularly on &amp;ldquo;Data Science for Sustainable Cities&amp;rdquo;. My talk is titled: &amp;ldquo;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&amp;rdquo;; which is the work I am doing as part of my PhD research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incase you missed it: My Webinar on Spatial Data Analysis with R</title>
      <link>/post/2016/02/25/incase-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 17:22:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/02/25/incase-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R&amp;rdquo;, here is the recording.
 You can access the material used for this webinar from Domino Data Lab&amp;rsquo;s platform using the following links:
 The Slides [domino-presentation.pdf]
 The RMarkdown Script [ReadMe.Rmd]
 The Whole Project [All files including data]
  If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. If you have more topics (related to R) that you are interested in learning about, send them my way so we can prepare another webinar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinar: Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R</title>
      <link>/post/2016/02/15/webinar-getting-started-with-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 17:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/02/15/webinar-getting-started-with-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>I am glad to announce that I shall be presenting a live webinar with Domino Data Labs on February 24, 2016 from 11:00 - 11:30 AM PST: Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R. If you are interested or know someone interested in learning how to manipulate spatial and spatial-temporal data with R, please send them along. Here is the abstract:
Synopsis Spatial and spatial-temporal data have become pervasive.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking ggplot2 Extensions</title>
      <link>/post/2016/02/01/tracking-ggplot2-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 23:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/02/01/tracking-ggplot2-extensions/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The purpose of this blog post is to inform R users of a website that I created to track and list ggplot2 extensions. The site is available at: http://ggplot2-exts.github.io. The purpose of this site is to help other R users easily find ggplot2 extensions that are coming in &amp;ldquo;fast and furious&amp;rdquo; from the R community.
If you have developed or intend on developing ggplot2 extensions, submit them so that other R users can easily find them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Apache SparkR to Power Shiny Applications: Part I</title>
      <link>/post/2015/12/08/using-apache-sparkr-to-power-shiny-applications-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 17:24:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015/12/08/using-apache-sparkr-to-power-shiny-applications-part-i/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The objective of this blog post is demonstrate how to use Apache SparkR to power Shiny applications. I have been curious about what the use cases for a &amp;ldquo;Shiny-SparkR&amp;rdquo; application would be and how to develop and deploy such an app.
SparkR is an R package that provides a light-weight frontend to use Apache Spark from R. SparkR provides a distributed data frame implementation that supports operations like selection, filtering, aggregation etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launch Apache Spark on AWS EC2 and Initialize SparkR Using RStudio</title>
      <link>/post/2015/11/10/launch-apache-spark-on-aws-ec2-and-initialize-sparkr-using-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 09:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015/11/10/launch-apache-spark-on-aws-ec2-and-initialize-sparkr-using-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
In this blog post, we shall learn how to launch a Spark stand alone cluster on Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) for analysis of Big Data. This is a continuation from our previous blog, which showed us how to download Apache Spark and start SparkR locally on windows OS and RStudio.
We shall use Spark 1.5.1 (released on October 02, 2015) which has a spark-ec2 script that is used to install stand alone Spark on AWS EC2.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>