<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian on Daniel Emaasit</title>
    <link>/categories/bayesian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian on Daniel Emaasit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Daniel Emaasit</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/bayesian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Principled AI with Probabilistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2018/05/22/principled-ai-with-probabilistic-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/05/22/principled-ai-with-probabilistic-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>(Note: Cross-posted with the Haystax Technology Blog.)
At Haystax Technology, we are proponents and early adopters of principled approaches to machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) for cybersecurity.
We use the term &amp;lsquo;principled AI&amp;rsquo; to describe what we call our model-based approach, which is built on coherent mathematical principles. These principles help us keep our AI transparent, explainable and interpretable. Most importantly, they enable our systems to quantify uncertainty, unlike the black-box approach of deep neural networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Processes with Spectral Mixture Kernels to Implicitly Capture Hidden Structure from Data</title>
      <link>/post/2018/03/19/gaussian-processes-with-spectral-mixture-kernels-to-implicitly-capture-hidden-structure-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/03/19/gaussian-processes-with-spectral-mixture-kernels-to-implicitly-capture-hidden-structure-from-data/</guid>
      <description>(Note: Cross-posted with the Haystax Technology Blog.)
Several scientific fields such as insider-threat detection, highway-safety planning, often lack sufficient amounts of time-series training data for the purpose of scientific discovery. Moreover, the available limited data are quite noisy. For instance Greitzer and Ferryman (2013) state that ”ground truth” data on actual insider behavior is typically either not available or is limited. In some cases, one might acquire real data, but for privacy reasons, there is no attribution of any individuals relating to abuses or offenses i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICYMI: Probabilistic Programming Roundup November 2017</title>
      <link>/post/2017/12/04/icymi-probabilistic-programming-roundup-november-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/12/04/icymi-probabilistic-programming-roundup-november-2017/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed them, here are some articles from November 2017 of particular interest to users of Probabilistic Programming Languages(PPL).
 Uber AI Lab open sourced their deep probabilistic programming language called Pyro. Pyro is a tool for deep probabilistic modeling, unifying the best of modern deeplearning and Bayesian modeling.
 PyMC3 documentation was improved with new styling and builds on travis. You can help at this link.
 Prof.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICYMI: My talk on Introduction to Probabilistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2017/08/14/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/08/14/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>Incase you missed it, here is a recording of my talk on Introduction to Probabilisitic Machine Learning at the Las Vegas R &amp;amp; Data Science Meetup groups.
I introduced probabilistic machine learning and probabilistic programming with Stan. I discussed the basics of machine learning from a probabilistic/Bayesian perspective and contrasted it with traditional/algorithmic machine learning. I also discussed how to build probabilistic models in computer code using a new exciting programming paradigm called Probabilistic Programming (PP).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In case you missed it: My Webinar on Model-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 07:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;Model-Based Machine Learning&amp;rdquo;, here is the recording.
  Apologies for the poor quality of the video. Domino Data Lab&amp;rsquo;s webinar platform suffered a service degradation while recording the event. The webinar slides may be found below.
 If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. Finally, I would like to thank Daniel Enthoven and Daniel Chalef from Domino Data Lab for setting up this webinar.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>