<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Big Data on Daniel Emaasit</title>
    <link>/categories/big-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Big Data on Daniel Emaasit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Daniel Emaasit</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 07:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/big-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>In case you missed it: My Webinar on Model-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 07:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/08/03/in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;Model-Based Machine Learning&amp;rdquo;, here is the recording.
  Apologies for the poor quality of the video. Domino Data Lab&amp;rsquo;s webinar platform suffered a service degradation while recording the event. The webinar slides may be found below.
 If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. Finally, I would like to thank Daniel Enthoven and Daniel Chalef from Domino Data Lab for setting up this webinar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incase you missed it: My Talk at the United Nations Global Pulse Workshop</title>
      <link>/post/2016/07/07/incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 23:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/07/07/incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</guid>
      <description>In case you missed my talk at the 2016 Data Science Africa Workshop organized by the United Nations Global Pulse Lab, here is the recording. My talk was titled &amp;ldquo;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&amp;rdquo;.
 You can download slides for my talk from here.
 There were also talks from my colleagues at IBM Research - Africa including Oliver Bent, Simone Fobi and Skyler Speakman who gave a general overview of the work we are doing in our lab in Nairobi, Kenya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Preview of My Talk for the Data Science Africa Workshop organized by the United Nations</title>
      <link>/post/2016/06/28/a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:36:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016/06/28/a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to be invited by the United Nations Global Pulse lab to speak at the 2nd Data Science Africa Workshop scheduled to take place in Kampala, Uganda from 30th June to 1st July. The theme of this workshop is &amp;ldquo;Using data science to monitor and achieve the global goals (UNDP goals) in Africa&amp;rdquo;. I will be speaking particularly on &amp;ldquo;Data Science for Sustainable Cities&amp;rdquo;. My talk is titled: &amp;ldquo;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&amp;rdquo;; which is the work I am doing as part of my PhD research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Apache SparkR to Power Shiny Applications: Part I</title>
      <link>/post/2015/12/08/using-apache-sparkr-to-power-shiny-applications-part-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 17:24:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015/12/08/using-apache-sparkr-to-power-shiny-applications-part-i/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The objective of this blog post is demonstrate how to use Apache SparkR to power Shiny applications. I have been curious about what the use cases for a &amp;ldquo;Shiny-SparkR&amp;rdquo; application would be and how to develop and deploy such an app.
SparkR is an R package that provides a light-weight frontend to use Apache Spark from R. SparkR provides a distributed data frame implementation that supports operations like selection, filtering, aggregation etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launch Apache Spark on AWS EC2 and Initialize SparkR Using RStudio</title>
      <link>/post/2015/11/10/launch-apache-spark-on-aws-ec2-and-initialize-sparkr-using-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 09:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015/11/10/launch-apache-spark-on-aws-ec2-and-initialize-sparkr-using-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
In this blog post, we shall learn how to launch a Spark stand alone cluster on Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2) for analysis of Big Data. This is a continuation from our previous blog, which showed us how to download Apache Spark and start SparkR locally on windows OS and RStudio.
We shall use Spark 1.5.1 (released on October 02, 2015) which has a spark-ec2 script that is used to install stand alone Spark on AWS EC2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing and Starting SparkR Locally on Windows OS and RStudio</title>
      <link>/post/2015/07/26/installing-and-starting-sparkr-locally-on-windows-8-1-and-rstudio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 09:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015/07/26/installing-and-starting-sparkr-locally-on-windows-8-1-and-rstudio/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
With the recent release of Apache Spark 1.4.1 on July 15th, 2015, I wanted to write a step-by-step guide to help new users get up and running with SparkR locally on a Windows machine using command shell and RStudio. SparkR provides an R frontend to Apache Spark and using Spark’s distributed computation engine allows R-Users to run large scale data analysis from the R shell. The steps listed here WILL also be documented in my upcoming online book titled &amp;ldquo;Getting Started with SparkR for Big Data Analysis&amp;rdquo; which can be accessed at: http://www.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>