<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel Emaasit on Daniel Emaasit</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Daniel Emaasit on Daniel Emaasit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Daniel Emaasit</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An Integrated Travel Demand Model of Work Duration and Commute-mode Choices: A Flexible Modeling Approach</title>
      <link>/publication/integrated-tdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/integrated-tdm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICYMI: My talk on Introduction to Probabilistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/2017/08/07/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/08/07/introduction-to-probabilistic-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Incase you missed it, here is a recording of my talk on Introduction to Probabilisitic Machine Learning at the Las Vegas R &amp;amp; Data Science Meetup groups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Processes in Stan</title>
      <link>/talk/gaussian-processes-in-stan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/gaussian-processes-in-stan/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-requisites&#34;&gt;Pre-requisites:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please come with a laptop with the following software installed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R + RStudio:- Follow this link to install R. Also install the LATEST version of RStudio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rstan:- Follow this link to install rstan on MacOS/Linux or this link for Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bayesplot:- Follow this link to install bayesplot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speaker-bio&#34;&gt;Speaker Bio:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Emaasit is a PhD student of Transportation Engineering at UNLV. His research interests involve developing flexible probabilistic/Bayesian machine learning models for high-dimensional data with applications to urban mobility, travel demand modeling, and highway safety analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Probabilistic Machine Learning with Stan</title>
      <link>/talk/intro-pml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/intro-pml/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-requisites&#34;&gt;Pre-requisites:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please come with a laptop with the following software installed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R + RStudio:- Follow this link to install R. Also install the LATEST version of RStudio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rstan:- Follow this link to install rstan on MacOS/Linux or this link for Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bayesplot:- Follow this link to install bayesplot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speaker-bio&#34;&gt;Speaker Bio:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Emaasit is a PhD student of Transportation Engineering at UNLV. His research interests involve developing flexible probabilistic/Bayesian machine learning models for high-dimensional data with applications to urban mobility, travel demand modeling, and highway safety analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In case you missed it: My Webinar on Model-Based Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/2016/08/03/content/post/2016-08-03-in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 07:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/08/03/content/post/2016-08-03-in-case-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-model-based-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://danielemaasit.com/post/2016/07/16/webinar-model-based-machine-learning-and-probabilistic-programming-using-rstan/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Model-Based Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;,  here is the recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/175956118&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/175956118&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the poor quality of the video. Domino Data Lab&amp;rsquo;s webinar platform suffered a service degradation while recording the event. The webinar slides may be found below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[slideshare id=64647075&amp;amp;doc=3rdpresentationpaperreview-160803065711]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. Finally, I would like to thank &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/enthoven&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Daniel Enthoven&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/danielchalef&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Daniel Chalef&lt;/a&gt; from Domino Data Lab for setting up this webinar.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gallery of ggplot2 Extensions</title>
      <link>/2016/07/29/content/post/2016-07-29-a-gallery-of-ggplot2-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 02:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/29/content/post/2016-07-29-a-gallery-of-ggplot2-extensions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I announced the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ggplot2-exts.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2-extensions website&lt;/a&gt; which tracks and lists extensions built on top of the popular R visualization package &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.ggplot2.org/current/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I wanted to make it even easier for R users to filter and search for these extensions and so I have added a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ggplot2-exts.org/gallery/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gallery page&lt;/a&gt;. You can now search packages based on a filter like: if it&amp;rsquo;s on CRAN; or if  it&amp;rsquo;s for a particular task e.g. time series, networks, tech, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/07/gallery.png&#34; alt=&#34;gallery&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now easier for R developers to add their extensions to this Gallery. Submit a pull request by following these &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/gallery#adding-a-ggplot2-extension&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;simple instructions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Fork the gallery [repository](https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/gallery) on Github.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Create a png thumbnail of an interesting plot from your extension that will look good on a retina screen at 350x300 pixels and put this file in the `images` directory of [the gallery repository](https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/gallery).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Add an entry for your extension in the `_config.yml` file of [the repository](https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/gallery) with the meta data for your extension.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Push your changes and create a pull request.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/strong&gt;: Special thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryanhafen.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Ryan Hafen&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hafenstats&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@hafenstats&lt;/a&gt;) for inspiring the design of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ggplot2-exts.org/gallery/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Gallery page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinar: Model-Based Machine Learning and Probabilistic Programming using RStan</title>
      <link>/2016/07/16/content/post/2016-07-16-webinar-model-based-machine-learning-and-probabilistic-programming-using-rstan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 22:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/16/content/post/2016-07-16-webinar-model-based-machine-learning-and-probabilistic-programming-using-rstan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/07/mbml-webinar2.png&#34; alt=&#34;mbml-webinar2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad to announce that I shall be presenting a live webinar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Domino Data Labs&lt;/a&gt; on July 20, 2016 from 11:00 - 11:30 AM PST on &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.dominodatalab.com/an-introduction-to-model-based-machine-learning/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Model-Based Machine Learning and Probabilistic Programming using RStan&lt;/a&gt;. If you are interested in adopting machine learning but are overwhelmed by the vast amount of learning algorithms, this webinar will show how to overcome that challenge. This &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.dominodatalab.com/an-introduction-to-model-based-machine-learning/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; describes most of the material we will cover in the webinar. Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/resource/webinar/model-based-machine-learning&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;abstract&lt;/a&gt; for the webinar:
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&gt; 
&gt; ## Synopsis
&gt; 
&gt; 

&gt; 
&gt; In the last several decades, thousands of machine learning algorithms have been developed. Very often, the selection of an algorithm to solve a particular problem is driven more by the data scientist&#39;s familiarity with a small subset of available algorithms, than optimizing for predictive power or operational constraints. This is unsurprising: Newcomers to machine learning and veteran data scientists alike, may be overwhelmed by the multitude of machine learning algorithms and where and how it is most appropriate to use them.
&gt; 
&gt; 

&gt; 
&gt; In this webinar, Daniel Emaasit will introduce Model-Based Machine Learning (MBML), an approach to machine learning which addresses these challenges. Daniel will discuss the various uses of MBML, from tasks such as classification, to regression and clustering, and how it allows data scientists to address the uncretainty inherent to real-world machine learning applications. Daniel will demonstrate how to implement MBML in a probabilistic programming language called Stan, using the RStan package. At the end of webinar, attendees will have the knowledge to build their own custom probabilistic models, learning their parameters from data.
&gt; 
&gt; 
![Daniel Emaasit](https://www.dominodatalab.com/images/resources/daniel-e.jpg)

&gt; 
&gt; ## About the Speaker
&gt; 
&gt; 
Daniel Emaasit is a Ph.D Student of Transportation Engineering at UNLV, where his research interests involve the development of probabilistic machine learning methods for high-dimensional data, with applications to urban mobility, transport planning, highway safety, &amp; traffic operations.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/resource/webinar/model-based-machine-learning&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to register for the webinar. I look forward to seeing you there and answering your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incase you missed it: My Talk at the United Nations Global Pulse Workshop</title>
      <link>/2016/07/07/content/post/2016-07-07-incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 23:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/07/07/content/post/2016-07-07-incase-you-missed-it-my-talk-at-the-united-nations-global-pulse-worshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you missed my talk at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa2016/#workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2016 Data Science Africa Workshop&lt;/a&gt; organized by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://unglobalpulse.org/kampala&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;United Nations Global Pulse Lab&lt;/a&gt;, here is the recording. My talk was titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.danielemaasit.com/2016/06/28/a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/47IjdD2yyGE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/47IjdD2yyGE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download slides for my talk from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/v53ymxth8x4hpe1/dsa_2016_presentation.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[slideshare id=63828079&amp;amp;doc=dsa2016presentation-160707230510]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also talks from my colleagues at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.ibm.com/labs/africa/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IBM Research - Africa&lt;/a&gt; including Oliver Bent, Simone Fobi and Skyler Speakman who gave a general overview of the work we are doing in our lab in Nairobi, Kenya. Here is their recording:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/gxFstDWf9VU&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/gxFstDWf9VU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Dr. John Quinn and the entire team a the &lt;a href=&#34;http://unglobalpulse.org/kampala&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UNGP - Kampala&lt;/a&gt; for the invitation to speak and for a well organized event.  You can read more about the workshop from this &lt;a href=&#34;http://unglobalpulse.org/news/data-science-in-africa-2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://unglobalpulse.org/blog&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;UNGP blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great meeting a lot of people from academia, industry, non-profits and government who are using Data Science to solve several challenges on the African continent, ranging from health care to agriculture and to sustainable cities. I look forward to attending more events in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;attachment_510&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;aligncenter&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;525&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/07/dsa-pic.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;dsa-pic&#34; /&gt; United Nations Global Pulse Lab Kampala and partners from academia, industry, non-profit, government came together for the second workshop on Data Science in Africa, which was organized between 27 June - 1 July in Kampala, Uganda[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Preview of My Talk for the Data Science Africa Workshop organized by the United Nations</title>
      <link>/2016/06/28/content/post/2016-06-28-a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:36:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/06/28/content/post/2016-06-28-a-preview-of-my-talk-for-the-data-science-africa-workshop-organized-by-the-united-nations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/un.png&#34; alt=&#34;un&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to be invited by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unglobalpulse.org/kampala&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;United Nations Global Pulse lab&lt;/a&gt; to speak at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.datascienceafrica.org/dsa2016/#workshop&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2nd Data Science Africa Workshop&lt;/a&gt; scheduled to take place in Kampala, Uganda from 30th June to 1st July. The theme of this workshop is &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Using data science to monitor and achieve the global goals (UNDP goals) in Africa&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. I will be speaking particularly on &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Data Science for Sustainable Cities&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. My talk is titled: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Sustainable Urban Transport Planning using Big Data from Mobile Phones&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;; which is the work I am doing as part of my PhD research. Particularly, I will talk about how developing countries can leverage low-cost, readily available and massive amounts of mobile phone data to improve their Transportation Planning policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/congestion1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;congestion1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past decades, there has been rapid urbanization as more and more people migrate into cities. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that by 2017, a majority of people will be living in urban areas. By 2030, 5 billion people—60 percent of the world’s population—will live in cities, compared with 3.6 billion in 2013. Developing nations must cope with this rapid urbanization. Transportation and urban planners must estimate travel demand for transportation facilities and use this to plan transportation infrastructure. Presently, the technique used for transportation planning uses data inputs from local and national household travel surveys. However, these surveys are expensive to conduct, cover smaller areas of cities and the time between surveys range from 5 to 10 years. This calls for new and innovative ways for Transportation Planning using new data sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, we have witnessed the proliferation of ubiquitous mobile computing devices in developing countries. These mobile phones capture the movement of vehicles and people in near real time and generate massive amounts of new data.  My PhD research investigates how we can utilize anonymized mobile phone data ( i.e. Call Detail Records) and probabilistic machine learning to infer travel/mobility patterns. One of the objectives of this research is to demonstrate that these new “big” data sources are cheaper alternatives for transport modeling and travel behavior studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll have various UN and government people doing urban planning who I think would enjoy this topic — see you there! .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t already, register for &lt;a href=&#34;http://goo.gl/forms/Et8ztKOQmo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Science Africa Workshop 2016 here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automating Hyperparameter tuning</title>
      <link>/project/auto-tdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/auto-tdm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Statistical estimation of integrated travel demand models (TDMs) is tedious and involves an iterative process which requires expert knowledge and time to perform several tasks including but not limited to: preprocessing data, selecting appropriate attributes, selecting appropriate models, finding model parameters, and critically analyzing results (Castiglione et al., 2015). Model estimation involves varying some free parameters, hyperparameters, to produce several models which are compared to select the most superior one. Considerable time and expertise are required to tune hyperparameters and consequently select appropriate models; which is prone to subjective error. The subjectivity of tuning hyperparameters for integrated TDMs makes published results difficult to reproduce, extend, and development is more an art than a science (Bergstra et al., 2011). There is a need for methods to minimize subjectivity in hyperparameter tuning and model selection.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Travel Demand Modeling</title>
      <link>/project/integrated-tdms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/integrated-tdms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Currently, there is growing research interest in integrated travel demand models that consider simultaneously many influencing factors that affect travel behavior (Pinjari et al., 2011; Pendyala et al., 2012). Integrated models are mathematical representations of real-world decision processes made by travelers. It is typical for travelers to simultaneously make several decisions, such as where to live and work, how many vehicles to own, and decisions regarding their daily activities and travel. Such decisions are made as part of an overall decision process rather than as independent choices exercised in a sequential manner (Pinjari et al., 2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the current literature focus on parametric models that impose strong restrictive assumptions by prespecifying the functional form and number of parameters (Habib et al., 2011; Pinjari et al., 2011; Habib, 2012). Prespecifying a functional form for a joint model could lead to either overly complex model specifications or simplistic models. It is difficult to know a priori the most appropriate function to use for modeling complex travel behavior that involve jointly made decision choices; long-term, medium-term, and short-term decisions; and many other influencing factors. Due to a finite number of parameters, parametric models are not necessarily the best to capture the entire structure of complex processes (Ghahramani, 2015), such as travel behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latent Travel Patterns from Mobile Phone Data</title>
      <link>/project/cdr-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cdr-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Data collected using intelligent transportation systems (ITS) technologies typically do not include information about the type of associated activity. For instance, cell-phone data typically consist of locations and time stamps of calls made and received. However, the corresponding activity-based travel patterns, such as working or shopping, are not as clear. Similarly, corresponding periodic variations of travel patterns as well as the distinct behavioral clusters of travelers are not explicitly provided in these data sets. Traditionally, these inexplicit (i.e., hidden patterns) are extracted by developing probabilistic models that attempt to explain the observed data. These models assume that the data were generated by an underlying latent process with parameters that can be inferred. In travel demand modeling, these underlying processes are the activities of travelers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existing literature has focused primarily on the use of parametric models to estimate travel activities. Hence, a priori bounds on model complexity and size (i.e. the number of latent activities) need to be imposed. In particular, inference using the standard expectation maximization (EM) algorithm involves pre-specifying the total number of unknown latent activities. Choosing very low bounds results in simple models that underestimate the number of actual activities. On the other hand, choosing too many activities may result in overly complex models that overfit or are expensive to compute. Hence, parametric models are not necessarily the best to capture unknown latent travel activities when using such ITS data sources as cell phone and GIS&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incase you missed it: My Webinar on Spatial Data Analysis with R</title>
      <link>/2016/02/25/content/post/2016-02-25-incase-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 17:22:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/02/25/content/post/2016-02-25-incase-you-missed-it-my-webinar-on-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you missed my free webinar on &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.danielemaasit.com/2016/02/15/webinar-getting-started-with-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;,  here is the recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/156607218&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/156607218&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can access the material used for this webinar from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Domino Data Lab&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s platform using the following links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Slides [&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.dominodatalab.com/SparkIQLabs/spatial-analysis/view/domino-presentation.pdf?commitId=fca395c2d9501d3282b24029fea7d16e6d8b91d0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;domino-presentation.pdf&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RMarkdown Script [&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.dominodatalab.com/SparkIQLabs/spatial-analysis/view/ReadMe.Rmd?commitId=fca395c2d9501d3282b24029fea7d16e6d8b91d0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ReadMe.Rmd&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://app.dominodatalab.com/SparkIQLabs/spatial-analysis/browse&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Whole Project&lt;/a&gt; [All files including data]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to contact me. If you have more topics (related to R) that you are interested in learning about, send them my way so we can prepare another webinar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to thank &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/annaanisin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Anna Anisin&lt;/a&gt; from Domino Data Lab for setting up this webinar.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webinar: Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R</title>
      <link>/2016/02/15/content/post/2016-02-15-webinar-getting-started-with-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 17:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/02/15/content/post/2016-02-15-webinar-getting-started-with-spatial-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/webinar3.png&#34; alt=&#34;webinar3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am glad to announce that I shall be presenting a live webinar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Domino Data Labs&lt;/a&gt; on February 24, 2016 from 11:00 - 11:30 AM PST: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/resource/webinar/getting_started_spacial_data_analysis_r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Spatial Data Analysis with R&lt;/a&gt;. If you are interested or know someone interested in learning how to manipulate spatial and spatial-temporal data with R, please send them along. Here is the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&gt; 
&gt; ## Synopsis
&gt; 
&gt; 
Spatial and spatial-temporal data have become pervasive. We are generating spatial data from route planners, sensors, mobile devices, and computers in different fields like transportation, agriculture, and social media. These data need to be analyzed to generate hidden insights that can improve business processes, help fight crime in cities, and much more.

Simply creating static maps is not enough. In this webinar we shall look at techniques of importing and exporting spatial data into R; understanding the foundation classes for spatial data; manipulation of spatial data; and techniques for spatial visualization. This webinar is meant to provide introductory knowledge of spatial data analysis in R needed to understand more complex spatial data modeling techniques.

We will cover the following topics:

&gt; 
&gt; 
    
&gt;   1. Why use R for spatial analysis
&gt; 
    
&gt;   2. Packages for spatial data analysis
&gt; 
    
&gt;   3. Types of spatial data
&gt; 
    
&gt;   4. Classes and methods in R for spatial data analysis
&gt; 
    
&gt;   5. Importing and exporting spatial data
&gt; 
    
&gt;   6. Visualizing spatial data in R
&gt; 


&gt; 
&gt; ## About the Speaker
&gt; 
&gt; 
![](https://www.dominodatalab.com/images/avatars/daniel-emaasit.jpg)

**Daniel Emaasit, Ph.D Student at University of Nevada, Las Vegas**

Daniel is a Ph.D Student of Transportation Engineering at UNLV where his research involves application of statistical machine learning to developing Activity-Based Travel Demand Models using Big Data from mobile phones. The objective of his research is to improve Transportation Planning by developing methods that model urban mobility patterns and trends.

He is an organizer of several Data Science and R meetup groups and actively contributes to open-source technologies in the R community.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominodatalab.com/resource/webinar/getting_started_spacial_data_analysis_r&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to register for the webinar. I look forward to seeing you there and answering your questions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tracking ggplot2 Extensions</title>
      <link>/2016/02/01/content/post/2016-02-01-tracking-ggplot2-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 23:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/02/01/content/post/2016-02-01-tracking-ggplot2-extensions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/ggplot2-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;ggplot2-2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this blog post is to inform R users of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; that I created to track and list &lt;strong&gt;ggplot2 extensions&lt;/strong&gt;. The site is available at: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io&lt;/a&gt;. The purpose of this site is to help other R users easily find &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt; extensions that are coming in &amp;ldquo;fast and furious&amp;rdquo; from the R community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have developed or intend on developing ggplot2 extensions, submit them so that other R users can easily find them. To do so, simply create an issue or a pull request on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/ggplot2-exts.github.io/tree/dev&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incase you are wondering what ggplot2 extensions are; these are R packages that extend the functionality of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2 package&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://had.co.nz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Hadley Wickham&lt;/a&gt;. This extensibility mechanism became available in ggplot2 version 2.0.0 &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.rstudio.org/2015/12/21/ggplot2-2-0-0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;released on December 17th, 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation-for-developing-this-website&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation for Developing this Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Hadley announced the release of ggplot2 2.0.0, perhaps the most exciting news was the addition of an official extension mechanism. This mechanism allows other R developers to easily create their on stats, geoms and positions, and provide them in other packages. This means that even when less development occurs in the ggplot2 package itself, the community will continue to release packages for graphical analysis that extend/solve different requirements. (To learn how you can develop your own extensions, there&amp;rsquo;s a step by step tutorial here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggplot2/vignettes/extending-ggplot2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggplot2/vignettes/extending-ggplot2.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after this announcement, several extensions started popping up. I was able to learn of some because they were posted out on twitter by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hadleywickham&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@hadleywickham&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/screenshot_2016-01-30-10-52-46-1.png?w=680&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot_2016-01-30-10-52-46-1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it got me thinking&amp;hellip;.. R users who are not active on social media must be missing out on these new cool extensions. In addition, if I didn&amp;rsquo;t check my twitter feed on a particular day, I would miss tweets about new extension-packages. This was not an effective way of searching for packages. There has to be a better way to track and list ggplot2 extensions. Quickly, I sprang into action to help fill this gap. But first, I had to find out if such an initiative already existed in the R community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/screenshot_2016-01-30-10-52-27-1.png?w=680&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot_2016-01-30-10-52-27-1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out none existed. I quickly started developing one and a couple of hours later, we had a working website (&lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io&lt;/a&gt;) with a list of extensions known to me then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/ggplot2-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;ggplot2-3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hadley was kind enough to inform his followers on twitter about this new initiative. (I should mention, it was the highlight of my life getting a &amp;ldquo;thumps up&amp;rdquo; from Hadley Wickham).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/screenshot_2016-02-01-15-12-16-1.png?w=680&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot_2016-02-01-15-12-16-1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I was not the only one concerned about this issue. Several other R users had made similar inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://emaasit.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/screenshot_2016-01-30-10-49-14-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot_2016-01-30-10-49-14-2&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-remarks&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Closing Remarks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In closing, I hope to see more cool extensions being developed and shared with the rest of the community on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ggplot2-exts.github.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ggplot2-exts.github.io&lt;/a&gt; so that other R Users can easily find them. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to create an issue or a pull request on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ggplot2-exts/ggplot2-exts.github.io/tree/dev&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
